You now know about the stochastic gradient descent algorithm.
But when you're running the algorithm,
how do you make sure that
it's completely debugged and is converging okay?
Equally important, how do
you tune the learning rate alpha
with Stochastic Gradient Descent.
In this video we talk about
some techniques for doing these things,
for making sure it's converging and
for picking the learning
rate alpha.
Back when we were using batch
gradient descent our standard way
for making sure that when the
set was converging was we
would plot the authorization cost
function as a function of the number of iterations.
So that was the cost function
and we would make sure that
this cost function is decreasing on every iteration.
When the training set sizes were
small we could do that because
we could compute the sum pretty
efficiently when you have
a massive training set size
then you don't want to have
to pause your algorithm periodically.
You don't want to have to stochastic
gradient descent periodically in order
to compute this cost function
since it requires a sum of your entire training set size.
And the whole point of stochastic
gradient was that you
wanted to start [XX] after
just looking at a single example without
needing to occasionally scan through
your entire training set right
in the middle of the algorithm
just to confuse things like the
cost function of the
entire training set converging,
here's what we can do instead.
Let's take the definition of the cost that we had previously.
So the cost of the parameters
theta with respect to a
single training example is just
one half of the square error on that training example.
Then, while stochastic gradient descent
is learning, right before
we we train on a specific example.
So, in stochastic gradient descent
we're going to look at the examples
xi, yi, in order, and
then sort of take a little update with respect to this example.
And we go on to the next
example, xi plus 1,
yi plus 1, and so on, right?
That's what stochastic gradient descent does.
So, while the algorithm
is looking at the example
xi, yi, but before
it has updated the parameters
theta using that um, example,
let's compute the cost of that example.
Just to say the same thing again, but using slightly different words.
stochastic gradient descent is
scanning through our training set
right before we have updated
theta using a specific training
example x i comma y
i let's compute how well
our hypothesis is doing on that training example.
And we want to do this before updating
theta because if we've
just updated theta using example,
you know, that it might be doing
better on that example than what would be representative.
Finally, in order to
check for the convergence [xx]  stochastic
gradient descent, what we can
do is every, say, every
thousand iterations, we can
plot these costs that we've been computing in the previous step.
We can plot those costs average
over, say, the last thousand
examples processed by the algorithm.
And if you do this, it kind
of gives you a running estimate
of how well the algorithm is doing.
on, you know, the last
1000 training examples that your has seen.
So, in contrast to computing
which needed to scan through the entire training set.
With this other procedure, well, as
part of stochastic gradient descent,
it doesn't cost much to compute
these costs as well right be updating to parameter theta.
And all we're doing is every thousand
integrations or so, we just
average the last 1,000 costs
that we computed and plot that.
And by looking at those
plots, this will allow
us to check if stochastic gradient descent is converging.
So here are a few examples
of what these plots might look like.
Suppose you have plotted the cost
average over the last thousand examples,
because these are averaged over
just a thousand examples they are
going to be a little bit noisy
and so, it may not
decrease on every single iteration.
Then if you get a figure that
looks like this, So the
plot is noisy because it's
average over, you know, just
a small subset, say a thousand training examples.
If you get a figure
that looks like this, you know
that would be a pretty decent
run with the algorithm, maybe, where
it looks like the cost has
gone down and then this
plateau that looks kind of
flattened out, you know, starting from around there.
look like, this is
what your cost looks like then maybe your learning algorithm has converged.
If you want to try using a
smaller learning rate, something you
might see is that the
algorithm may initially learn more
slowly so the cost goes down more slowly.
But then eventually you have a
smaller learning rate is actually possible
for the algorithm to end up
at a, maybe very slightly better solution.
So the red line may represent
the behavior of stochastic gradient descent
using a slower, using a
smaller And the
reason this is the case is
because, you remember, stochastic gradient
descent doesn't just converge
the global minimum, is that
what it does is the parameters
will oscillate a bit around the global minimum.
So by using a smaller learning
rate, you'll end up with smaller oscillations.
And Sometimes this little
difference will be negligible
and sometimes with a smaller
than you can get a slightly
better value for the parameters.
Here are some other things that might happen.
Let's say you run stochastic gradient
descent and you average over a
thousand examples when plotting these costs.
So, you know, here might be
the result of averaging another one of these plots.
Then again, it kind of looks like it's converged.
If you were to take this number,
a thousand, and increase to
averaging over 5 thousand examples.
Then it's possible that you might
get a smoother curve that looks more like this.
And by averaging over, say
5,000 examples instead of
1,000, you might be able
to get a smoother curve like this.
And so that's the effect of increasing the number of examples you have is your over.
The disadvantage of making this
too big of course is that
now you get one date point only every 5,000 examples.
And so the feedback you get
on how well your learning learning
algorithm is doing is, sort of,
maybe it's more delayed because you
get one data point on
your plot only every 5,000 examples rather than every 1,000 examples.
Along a similar vein some
times you may run a
gradient descent and end up with a plot that looks like this.
And with a plot that looks
like this, you know, it
looks like the cost just
is not decreasing at all.
It looks like the algorithm is just not learning.
It's just, looks like things
get flat, basically a flat curve and the cost is
just not decreasing but, again
if you were to increase this
to averaging over a larger
number of examples it is possible
that you see something like this
it looks like the cost
actually is decreasing, it's just
that the blue line averaging
over 2, 3 examples, the
blue line was too noisy so
you couldn't see the actual trend
in the cost actually decreasing
and possibly averaging over 5,000
examples instead of 1,000 may help.
Of course we averaged over a
larger number examples that we've
averaged here over 5,000
examples, I'm just using a different
color, it is also possible that you
that see a learning curve ends up looking like this.
That it's still fat even
when you average over a larger number of examples.
And as you get that, then
that's maybe just a more
firm verification that unfortunately
the algorithm just isn't learning much for whatever reason.
And you need to
either change the learning rate or
change the features or change something else about the algorithm.
Finally, one last thing that
you might see would be if
you were to plot these and
you see a curve that looks like
this, where it actually looks like it's increasing.
And if that's the case then this
is a sign that the algorithm is diverging.
And What you really should
do is use a smaller
value of the learning rate alpha.
So hopefully this gives you
a sense of the range of
phenomena you might see when
you plot these cost average over
some range of examples as well
as suggests the sorts
of things you might try to do
in response to seeing different plots.
So if the plots looks too noisy,
or if it wiggles up and
down too much, then try
increasing the number of
examples you're averaging over so
you can see the overall trend in the plot better.
And if you see that
the errors are actually increasing, the
costs are actually increasing, try
using a smaller value of alpha.
Finally, it's worth examining the
of the learning rate just a little bit more.
We saw that when we run stochastic
gradient descent, the algorithm will
start here and sort of
meander towards the minimum And
then it won't really converge, and
instead it'll wander around the minimum forever.
And so you end up with
a parameter value that is
hopefully close to the global
minimum that won't be exact at the global minimum.
In most typical implementations of stochastic
gradient descent the learning rate
alpha is typically held constant.
And so what you we end
up is exactly a picture
like this.
If you want stochastic gradient descent
to actually converge to the
global minimum, there's one thing
which you can do which is
You can slowly decrease the learning rate alpha over time.
So, a pretty typical way
of doing that would be
to set alpha equals some
constant one divided by iteration
number plus constant 2.
So, iteration number is the
number of iterations you've run
of stochastic gradient descent,
so it's really the number of
training examples you've And counts
1 and counts 2 are
additional parameters that you have
that you might have to play
with a bit in order to get good performance.
reasons people tend not to
do this is because you end
up needing to spend time playing
with these 2 extra parameters, constant
1 and constant 2, and so this makes the algorithm more finicky.
You know, it's just more parameters able
to fiddle with in order to make the algorithm work well.
But if you manage to tune
the parameters well, then the
picture you can get is that
the algorithm will actually around towards
the minimum, but as it gets
closer because you're decreasing the
learning rate the meanderings will
get smaller and smaller until
it pretty much just to the global minimum.
I hope this makes sense, right?
And the reason this formula makes
sense is because as the
algorithm runs, the iteration number becomes
large So alpha will slowly
become small, and so
you take smaller and smaller steps
until it sort of, you
know, hopefully converges to the global minimum.
So If you do slowly decrease
alpha to zero you can end up with a slightly better hypothesis.
But because of the extra work
needed for the constants and because frankly you.
we're pretty happy with any
parameter value that is, you know, pretty close to the global minimum.
Typically this process of decreasing
alpha slowly is usually not
done and Keeping the learning.
Alpha constant is the more
common application of stochastic
gradient descent although you will see people use either version.
To summarize in this video
we talk about a way for
approximately monitoring how the
stochastic gradient descent is doing
in terms for optimizing the cost function.
And this is a method that
does not require scanning over
the entire training set periodically
to compute the cost function.
But instead it looks
at say only the last thousand
examples or so.
And you can use this method both
to make sure the stochastic gradient
descent is okay and is converging
or to use it to tune the learning rate alpha.