In the previous video, we talked
about Stochastic gradient descent,
and how that can be much faster than Batch gradient descent.
In this video, let's talk about another variation on these ideas
is
called Mini-batch gradient descent
they can work sometimes even a
bit faster than stochastic gradient descent.
To summarize the algorithms we talked about so far.
In Batch gradient descent we
will use all m examples in each generation.
Whereas in Stochastic gradient
descent we will use
a single example in each generation.
What Mini-batch gradient descent does is somewhere in between.
Specifically, with this algorithm we're going to use
b examples in each
iteration where b is
a parameter called the mini
batch size so the
idea is that this
is somewhat in-between Batch gradient descent and Stochastic gradient descent.
This is just like batch gradient
descent, except that I'm going to use a much smaller batch size.
A typical tourist for the
value of b might be
b equals 10 lets say
and a typical range really might
be anywhere from b equals 2
up to b equals 100.
So that will be a pretty typical
range of values for the
Mini-batch size.
And the idea is that
rather than using one example
at a time or m examples
at a time we will use b examples at a time.
So let me just
write this off informally, we're going
to get, let's say, b.
For this example, let's say b equals 10.
So we're going to get, you
know, the next 10 examples from
my training set so that
may be some set of
examples xi, yi.
If it's 10 examples then the
indexing will be up
to x (i+9),
y (i+9)
so that's 10 examples altogether and
then we'll perform essentially a
gradient descent update using these
10 examples. So, that's
any rate times one tenth times
sum over k equals
i through i+9 of x subscript theta of x(k)
minus y(k) you times
x(k)j.
And so
in this expression, where summing the
gradient terms over my ten examples.
So, that's number ten, that's, you know, my mini
batch size and just i+9
again, the 9
comes from the choice of
the parameter b, and then
after this we will then
increase, you know, i by
tenth, we will go on
to the next ten examples and then
keep moving like this. So just
to write out the entire algorithm in
full. In order to
simplify the indexing for
this one at the
right top, I'm going to
assume we have a mini-batch size of
ten and a training
set size of a thousand, what we're
going to do is have this
sort of form, you know, for i
equals 1 and that in 21's
the stepping, in steps of
10 because we look at
10 examples at a time.
And then we perform this sort of
gradient descent update using
ten examples at a time
so this 10 and this
i+9 those are consequence
of having chosen my mini-batch to be ten.
And you know, this ultimate four-loop, this ends at 991
here because if I
have 1000 training samples then
I need 100 steps of size
10 in order to get through my training set.
So this is mini-batch gradient descent.
Compared to batch gradient
descent, this also allows us to make progress much faster.
So we have again our
running example of, you know,
U.S. Census data with 300
million training examples, then what
we're saying is after looking at
just the first 10 examples
we can start to make progress
in improving the parameters
theta so we don't' need
to scan through the entire training set.
We just need to look
at the first 10 examples
and this will start letting us make
progress and then we can look at the second ten examples and modify the parameters a little bit again
and so on. So, that
is why Mini-batch gradient descent can be faster
than batch gradient descent.
Namely, you can start making progress
in modifying the parameters after
looking at just ten examples rather
than needing to wait 'till
you've scan through every single training
example of 300 million of them.
So, how about Mini-batch
gradient descent versus Stochastic gradient descent.
So, why do we
want to look at b examples
at a time rather than
look at just a single example
at a time as the Stochastic gradient descent?
The answer is in vectorization.
In particular, Mini-batch
gradient descent is likely to
outperform Stochastic gradient descent
only if you have a good vectorized
implementation.
In that case, the sum over
10 examples can be
performed in a more vectorized way
which will allow you to
partially parallelize your computation over the ten examples.
So, in other words, by using
appropriate vectorization to compute
the rest of the terms, you can
sometimes partially use the
good numerical algebra libraries and
parallelize your gradient computations
over the b examples, whereas if
you were looking at just a
single example of time with Stochastic
gradient descent then you know
just looking at one example at a time their isn't much to parallelize over.
At least there is less to parallelize over.
One disadvantage of Mini-batch
gradient descent is that there is now
this extra parameter b, the
Mini-batch size which you
may have to fiddle with, and which may therefore take time.
But if you have a good
vectorized implementation this can
sometimes run even faster that Stochastic gradient descent.
So that was Mini-batch
gradient descent which is an
algorithm that in some sense
does something that's somewhat in
between what Stochastic gradient descent does and what Batch gradient descent does.
And if you
choose their reasonable value of b. I usually
use b equals 10, but,
you know, other values, anywhere from
say 2 to 100, would be reasonably common.
So we choose value of
b and if you use
a good vectorized implementation, sometimes t
can be faster than both Stochastic
gradient descent and faster than Batch gradient descent.