In the next few videos, we'll talk about large scale machine learning.
That is algorithms but viewing with big data sets.
If you look back and a
recent 5 or 10-year history of machine learning.
One of the reasons that learning
albums works so much better
now than even say, 5-years
ago, is just the sheer
amount of data that we
have now and that we can trade our algorithms on.
In these next few videos,
we'll talk about algorithms for dealing
when we have such massive
data sets. So why
do we want to use such large data sets?
We've already seen that one
of the best ways to get
a high performance machine learning
system, is if you
take a low-bias learning algorithm, and
train that on a lot of data.
And so, one early
example already seen was
this example of cos sin between confusable words.
So, for breakfast, I ate two
eggs and we saw in
this example, these sorts
of results, where, you know, so long
as you feed the algorithm a lot
of data, it seems to do very well.
And so it's results like these
that has led to the saying
in machine learning that often it's
not who has the best algorithm that wins.
It's who has the most data.
So you want to learn
from large data sets, at
least when we can get such large data sets.
But learning with large data sets
comes with its own unique
problems, specifically, computational problems.
Let's say your training set size
is M equals 100,000,000.
And this is actually pretty
realistic for many modern data sets.
If you look at the US Census
data set, if there
are, you know, 300 million people in the
US, you can usually get hundreds of millions of records.
If you look at the amount of
traffic that popular websites get, you
easily get training sets that are much larger than hundreds of millions of examples.
And let's say you want
to train a linear regression model
or maybe a logistic regression model,
in which case this is the gradient descent rule.
And if you look at what
you need to do to compute
the gradient, which is this
term over here, then when
M is a hundred million,
you need to carry out a summation
over a hundred million terms,
in order to compute these derivatives
terms and to perform a single step of decent.
Because of the computational expense of
summing over a hundred million
entries in order to
compute just one step of
gradient descent, in the next
few videos we've spoken about techniques
for either replacing this with
something else or to
find more efficient ways to compute this derivative.
By the end of this sequence
of videos on large scale machine
learning, you know how
to fit models, linear regression, logistic regression, neural networks and so on even
two data sets with, say, a hundred million examples.
Of course, before we
put in the effort into training
a model with a hundred million
examples, We should also ask
ourselves, well, why not
use just a thousand examples.
Maybe we can randomly pick the
subsets of a thousand examples
out of a hundred million
examples and train our algorithm
on just a thousand examples.
So before investing the effort
into actually developing and
the software needed to train these
massive models is often a
good sanity check, if
training on just a thousand
examples might do just as well.
The way to sanity check of
using a much smaller training
set might do just as
well, that is if using
a much smaller n equals 1000 size
training set, that might do just
as well, it is the usual
method of plotting the learning
curves, so if you
were to plot the learning
curves and if your training
objective were to look
like this, that's J train theta.
And if your cross-validation set
objective, Jcv of theta
would look like this, then this
looks like a high-variance learning
algorithm, and we will
be more confident that adding
extra training examples would improve performance.
Whereas in contrast if you
were to plot the learning
curves, if your training
objective were to look like
this, and if your
trans-validation objective were to
look like that, then this looks
like the classical high-bias learning algorithm.
And in the latter case, you know, if
you were to plot this up to,
say, m equals 1000 and so
that is m equals 500 up
to m equals 1000, then it
seems unlikely that increasing m
to a hundred million will
do much better and then you'd
be just fine sticking to n equals 1000,
rather than investing a lot
of effort to figure out how the scale of the algorithm.
Of course, if you were in
the situation shown by the
figure on the right, then one
natural thing to do would
be to add extra features,
or add extra hidden units
to your neural network and
so on, so that you
end up with a situation
closer to that on the
left, where maybe this is up to
n equals 1000, and this then
gives you more confidence that trying
to add infrastructure to
change the algorithm to use
much more than a thousand examples
that might actually be a good use of your time.
So in large-scale machine learning,
we like to come up with
computationally reasonable ways, or
computationally efficient ways, to deal with very big data sets.
In the next few videos, we'll see two main ideas.
The first is called cost and
gradient descent and the second
is called Map Reduce, for viewing with very big data sets.
And after you've learned about
these methods, hopefully that will
allow you to scale up your
learning algorithms to big data
and allow you to get much
better performance on many different applications.