In the last video, we talked
about precision and recall as
an evaluation metric for classification
problems with skew classes.
For many applications, we'll want
to somehow control the trade
off between position and recall.
Let me tell you how
to do that and also show
you some, even more effective
ways to use precision and
recall as an evaluation
metric for learning algorithms.
As a reminder, here are the
definitions of precision and
recall from the previous video.
Let's continue our cancer classification
example, where y equals
one if the patient has cancer
and y equals zero otherwise.
And let's say we've trained in
logistic regression classifier, which outputs
probabilities between zero and one.
So, as usual, we're
going to predict one, y equals
one if h of x
is greater than or equal to
0.5 and predict zero if
the hypothesis outputs a value
less than 0.5 and this
classifier may give us
some value for precision and some value for recall.
But now, suppose we want
to predict that a patient
has cancer only if we're
very confident that they really do.
Because you know if you go
to a patient and you tell
them that they have cancer, it's
going to give them a huge
shock because this is seriously
bad news and they may
end up going through a pretty
painful treatment process and so on.
And so maybe we want to
tell someone that we think
they have cancer only if they're very confident.
One way to do this would
be to modify the algorithm, so
that instead of setting the
threshold at 0.5, we
might instead say that we'll
predict that y is equal
to 1, only if H of
x is greater than or equal to 0.7.
So this, I think
will tell someone if they
have cancer only if we think
there's a greater than, greater
than or equal to 70% that they have cancer.
And if you do this then
you're predicting some of this
cancer only when you're
more confident, and so
you end up with a classifier
that has higher precision, because
all the patients that you're
going to and say, you know,
we think you have cancer, all
of those patients are now
pretty, once they hear, pretty
confident they actually have cancer.
And so, a higher fraction of
the patients that you predict to
have cancer, will actually turn
out to have cancer, because in
making those predictions we are pretty confident.
But in contrast, this classifier will
have lower recall, because
now we are going
to make predictions, we are
going to predict y equals one, on a smaller number of patients.
Now we could even take this further.
Instead of setting the threshold
at 0.7, we can set
this at 0.9 and we'll predict
y1 only if we are
more than 90% certain that
the patient has cancer, and so,
you know, a large fraction that
those patients will turn out
to have cancer and so,
this is the high precision classifier
will have lower recall because we
want to correctly detect that those patients have cancer.
Now consider a different example.
Suppose we want to avoid
missing too many actual cases of cancer.
So we want to avoid the false negatives.
In particular, if a patient
actually has cancer, but we
fail to tell them that
they have cancer, then that can be really bad.
Because if we tell
a patient that they don't
have cancer then they are
not going to go for treatment and
if it turns out that they
have cancer or we fail
to tell them they have
cancer, well they may not get treated at all.
And so that would be
a really bad outcome because he
died because we told them
they don't have cancer they failed
to get treated, but it turns
out that they actually have cancer.
When in doubt, we want to
predict that y equals one.
So when in doubt, we want
to predict that they have
cancer so that at least
they look further into it
and this can get treated,
in case they do turn out to have cancer.
In this case, rather than setting
higher probability threshold, we might
instead take this value
and this then sets it to
a lower value, so maybe
0.3 like so.
By doing so, we're saying
that, you know what, if we
think there's more than a 30%
chance that they have caner, we better
be more conservative and tell
them that they may have cancer,
so they can seek treatment if necessary.
And in this case, what
we would have is going to
be a higher recall classifier,
because we're going to
be correctly flagging a higher
fraction of all of
the patients that actually do have
cancer, but we're going
to end up with lower precision,
because the higher fraction of
the patients that we said have
cancer, the higher fraction of them will turn out not to have cancer after all.
And by the way, just as an
aside, when I talk
about this to other
students up until before, it's pretty amazing.
Some of my say is
how I can tell the story both ways.
Why we might want to have
higher precision or higher recall
and the story actually seems to work both ways.
But I hope the details of
the algorithm is true and the
more general principle is, depending
on where you want, whether
you want high precision, lower recall
or higher recall, lower precision, you
can end up predicting y equals
one when each of x is greater than some threshold.
And so, in general, for
most crossfires, there is going
to be a trade off between precision and recall.
And as you vary the value
of this threshold, this value,
this special that I have
joined here, you can actually
plot us some curve that
trades off precision and
recall, where a value
up here, this would correspond
to a very high value of
the threshold, maybe threshold equals
over 0.99, so that say, predict
y equals 1 only where
no more than 99 percent
confident, at least 99
percent probability this once, so
that will be a precision relatively
low recall, whereas the point
down here will correspond to
a value of the threshold that's
much lower, maybe 0.01.
When in doubt at all, put down y1.
And if you do that, you
end up with a much
lower precision higher recall crossfire.
And as you vary the threshold, if
you want, you can actually trace
all the curve from your crossfire
to see the range of different values you can get for precision recall.
And by the way, the position
recall curve can look like many different shapes.
Sometimes it'll look this, sometimes
it'll look like that.
Now, there are many different possible
shapes in the position of recall
curve, depending on the details of the crossfire.
So this raises another
interesting question which is, is
there a way to choose
this threshold automatically?
Or, more generally, if we have
a few different algorithms or a
few different ideas for algorithms, how
do we compare different precision recall numbers?
completely.
Suppose we have three different
learning algorithms, or actually maybe
these are three different learning algorithms, may
be these are the same algorithm, but just with different values for the threshold.
How do we decide which of these algorithms is best?
One of the things we talked
about earlier is the importance
of a single real number evaluation metric.
And that is the idea of
having a number that just
tells you how well is your Crossfire doing.
But by switching to the precision
recall metric, we've actually lost that.
We now have two real numbers.
And so we often end up
facing situations, like if
we are trying to compare algorithm 1
to algorithm 2, we
end up asking ourselves, Is a
position of point five and
a recall of point four, well
is that better or worse than
a position of point seven or
a recall point one?
If every time you try
on a new algorithm you end up
having to sit around and think
well, maybe point five
point four, is better than point
seven point one, maybe not, I do not know.
If you end up having to sit around and think and make these decisions.
that really slows down your
decision making process, for what
changes are useful to incorporate into your algorithm.
Where as in contrast, if we
had a single real number evaluation metric,
like a number that just
tells us is either algorithm 1 or is algorithm 2 better.
That helps us much more
quickly decide which algorithm to
go with and helps us
as well to much more quickly
evaluate different changes that we
may be contemplating for an algorithm.
So, how can we get
a single real number evaluation metric.
One natural thing that you
might try is to look
at the average between precision and recall.
So using p and r
to denote position and recall, what
you could do is just compute the
average and look at what crossfire
has the highest average value.
But this turns out not to
be such a good solution because, similar
to the example we had earlier,
it turns out that if we
have a crossfire that predicts
y1 all the time, then if
you do that, you can get a very high recall.
That's you end up with a very low value of Vision.
Conversely,if you have a crossfire
that predicts y0 almost all
the time, that is, if
it predicts y one very sparingly.
This corresponds to setting
a very high threshold using the notation of previous line.
And then you can actually
end up with a very high precision with a very low recall.
So the two extremes of either
are a very high threshold or a
very low threshold, neither of
them would give it paticularary good crossfire.
And we recognize that is
by seeing if we end
up with a very low
precision or a very low recall.
And if you just take the average of people's ro2.
One does the example the average
is actually highest for algorithm 3.
Even though you can get
that sort of performance by predicting
y1 all the time.
And that is just not a very good classifier, right?
You predict y equals one all
the time is just not a
useful classifier if all it does is prints out y equals one.
And so algorithm one or algorithm
two would be more
useful than algorithm three,
but in this example algorithm three
has a higher average value of
precision recall than algorithm one and two.
So we usually think of
this average of precision recall
as not a particularly good way to evaluate our learning algorithm.
In contrast, there is a
different way of combining precision recall.
It is called the f score and it uses that formula.
So, in this example, here are the f scores.
And so we would tell
from these f scores and
we'll say algorithm 1 has
the highest f score.
Algorithm 2 has the second highest and
algorithm 3 has the lowest and so
you know, if we go by
the f score, we would pick probably algorithm of 1 over the others.
The f score, which is also
called the f1 score,
is usually written f1 score
that I have here, but often people will just say f score.
It determines use is a
little bit like taking the
average of precision of recall,
but it gives the lower
value of precision and recall
- whichever it is - it gives it a higher weight.
And so, you see in
the numerator here that the
f score takes a product or position of equal.
And so, if either position is
0 or recall is equal to
0, the f score will
be equal to o. So
in that sense, it kind of combines position and recall.
but for the f score to
be large, both position
and recall have to be pretty large.
I should say that there are
many different possible formulas for
combining position and recall.
This f score formula is
really, maybe just one out
of a much larger number of
possibilities, but historically or
traditionally this is what
people in machine learning use.
And the term f score, you
know, it doesn't really mean
anything, so don't worry about
why it's called f score or f1 score.
But this usually gives
you the effect that you want
because if either position is
0 or recall is 0, this
gives you a very low f score.
And so, to have a
high f score you can't
need a preserve quality 1
and completely if p
equals zero or i
equals zero then this
gives you the f score equals zero.
Where as a perfect f
score, so if position equals
one and  [xx] equals
one that would give
you an f score that's
equal to one times one
over two times two.
So the f score will be
equal to 1 if you
have perfect precision and perfect recall.
And intermediate values between 0
and 1, this usually gives a
reasonable rank ordering of different classifiers.
So this video we talked
about the notion of trading
off between position and recall
and how we can vary the
threshold that we use to
decide whether to predict y
equals one or y equals zero.
This threshold that says do
we need to be at least
seventy percent confident or ninety
percent confident or whatever before
we predict y equals one and
by varying the threshold you
can control a trade off
between precision and recall.
Ross talked about the f score
which takes precision and recall
and gives you a single
real number evaluation metric.
And of course, if your goal is
to automatically set that
threshold, to decide which
one of y equals 1 or
y equals 0, one pretty
reasonable way to do that
would also be to try
a range of different values of thresholds.
So, try a range of values
of thresholds and evaluate these
different threshold on say your
cross validation set, and then
to pick whatever value of threshold
gives you the highest f score
on your cross validation setting.
That would be a pretty reasonable way
to automatically chose the threshold for your crossfire as well.