In this video I am going to define what is
probably the most common type of machine
learning problem, which is supervised
learning. I'll define supervised learning
more formally later, but it's probably
best to explain or start with an example
of what it is and we'll do the formal
definition later. Let's say you want to
predict housing prices. A while back, a
student collected data sets from the
Institute of Portland Oregon. And let's
say you plot a data set and it looks like
this. Here on the horizontal axis, the
size of different houses in square feet,
and on the vertical axis, the price of
different houses in thousands of dollars.
So. Given this data, let's say you have a
friend who owns a house that is, say 750
square feet and hoping to sell the house
and they want to know how much they can
get for the house. So how can the learning
algorithm help you? One thing a learning
algorithm might be able to do is put a
straight line through the data or to fit a
straight line to the data and, based on
that, it looks like maybe the house can be
sold for maybe about $150,000. But maybe this
isn't the only learning algorithm you can
use. There might be a better one. For
example, instead of sending a straight
line to the data, we might decide that
it's better to fit a quadratic
function or a second-order polynomial to
this data. And if you do that, and make a
prediction here, then it looks like, well,
maybe we can sell the house for closer to
$200,000. One of the things we'll talk
about later is how to choose and how to
decide do you want to fit a straight line
to the data or do you want to fit the
quadratic function to the data and there's
no fair picking whichever one gives your
friend the better house to sell. But each
of these would be a fine example of a
learning algorithm. So this is an example
of a supervised learning algorithm. And
the term supervised learning refers to the
fact that we gave the algorithm a data set
in which the "right answers" were
given. That is, we gave it a data set of
houses in which for every example in this
data set, we told it what is the right
price so what is the actual price that,
that house sold for and the toss of the
algorithm was to just produce more of
these right answers such as for this new
house, you know, that your friend may be
trying to sell. To define with a bit more
terminology this is also called a
regression problem and by regression
problem I mean we're trying to predict a
continuous value output. Namely the price.
So technically I guess prices can be
rounded off to the nearest cent. So maybe
prices are actually discrete values, but
usually we think of the price of a house
as a real number, as a scalar value, as
a continuous value number and the term
regression refers to the fact that we're
trying to predict the sort of continuous
values attribute. Here's another
supervised learning example, some friends
and I were actually working on this
earlier. Let's see you want to look at
medical records and try to predict of a
breast cancer as malignant or benign. If
someone discovers a breast tumor, a lump
in their breast, a malignant tumor is a
tumor that is harmful and dangerous and a
benign tumor is a tumor that is harmless.
So obviously people care a lot about this.
Let's see a collected data set and suppose
in your data set you have on your
horizontal axis the size of the tumor and
on the vertical axis I'm going to plot one
or zero, yes or no, whether or not these are
examples of tumors we've seen before are
malignant–which is one–or zero if not malignant
or benign. So let's say our data set looks
like this where we saw a tumor of this
size that turned out to be benign. One of
this size, one of this size. And so on.
And sadly we also saw a few malignant
tumors, one of that size, one of that
size, one of that size... So on. So this
example... I have five examples of benign
tumors shown down here, and five examples
of malignant tumors shown with a vertical
axis value of one. And let's say we have
a friend who tragically has a breast
tumor, and let's say her breast tumor size
is maybe somewhere around this value. The
machine learning question is, can you
estimate what is the probability, what is
the chance that a tumor is malignant
versus benign? To introduce a bit more
terminology this is an example of a
classification problem. The term
classification refers to the fact that
here we're trying to predict a discrete
value output: zero or one, malignant or
benign. And it turns out that in
classification problems sometimes you can
have more than two values for the two
possible values for the output. As a
concrete example maybe there are three
types of breast cancers and so you may try
to predict the discrete value of zero,
one, two, or three with zero being benign.
Benign tumor, so no cancer. And one may
mean, type one cancer, like, you have
three types of cancer, whatever type one
means. And two may mean a second type of
cancer, a three may mean a third type of
cancer. But this would also be a
classification problem, because this other
discrete value set of output corresponding
to, you know, no cancer, or cancer type
one, or cancer type two, or cancer type
three. In classification problems there is
another way to plot this data. Let me show
you what I mean. Let me use a slightly
different set of symbols to plot this
data. So if tumor size is going to be the
attribute that I'm going to use to predict
malignancy or benignness, I can also draw
my data like this. I'm going to use
different symbols to denote my benign and
malignant, or my negative and positive
examples. So instead of drawing crosses,
I'm now going to draw O's for the benign
tumors. Like so. And I'm going to keep
using X's to denote my malignant tumors.
Okay? I hope this is beginning to make
sense. All I did was I took, you know,
these, my data set on top and I just
mapped it down. To this real line like so.
And started to use different symbols,
circles and crosses, to denote malignant
versus benign examples. Now, in this
example we use only one feature or one
attribute, mainly, the tumor size in order
to predict whether the tumor is malignant
or benign. In other machine learning
problems when we have more than one
feature, more than one attribute. Here's
an example. Let's say that instead of just
knowing the tumor size, we know both the
age of the patients and the tumor size. In
that case maybe your data set will look
like this where I may have a set of patients
with those ages and that tumor size and
they look like this. And a different set
of patients, they look a little different,
whose tumors turn out to be malignant, as
denoted by the crosses. So, let's say you
have a friend who tragically has a
tumor. And maybe, their tumor size and age
falls around there. So given a data set
like this, what the learning algorithm
might do is throw the straight line
through the data to try to separate out
the malignant tumors from the benign ones
and, so the learning algorithm may decide
to throw the straight line like that to
separate out the two classes of tumors.
And. You know, with this, hopefully you
can decide that your friend's tumor is
more likely to if it's over there,
that hopefully your learning algorithm
will say that your friend's tumor falls on
this benign side and is therefore more
likely to be benign than malignant. In
this example we had two features, namely,
the age of the patient and the size of the
tumor. In other machine learning problems
we will often have more features, and my
friends that work on this problem, they
actually use other features like these,
which is clump thickness, the clump thickness of
the breast tumor. Uniformity of cell size
of the tumor. Uniformity of cell shape of
the tumor, and so on, and other features
as well. And it turns out one of the interes-,
most interesting learning algorithms that
we'll see in this class is a learning
algorithm that can deal with, not just two
or three or five features, but an infinite
number of features. On this slide, I've
listed a total of five different features.
Right, two on the axes and three more up here.
But it turns out that for some learning
problems, what you really want is not to
use, like, three or five features. But
instead, you want to use an infinite
number of features, an infinite number of
attributes, so that your learning
algorithm has lots of attributes or
features or cues with which to make those
predictions. So how do you deal with an
infinite number of features. How do you even
store an infinite number of
things on the computer when your
computer is gonna run out of memory. It
turns out that when we talk about an
algorithm called the Support Vector
Machine, there will be a neat mathematical
trick that will allow a computer to deal
with an infinite number of features. Imagine
that I didn't just write down two features
here and three features on the right. But, imagine that
I wrote down an infinitely long list, I
just kept writing more and more and more
features. Like an infinitely long list of
features. Turns out, we'll be able to come
up with an algorithm that can deal with
that. So, just to recap. In this
class we'll talk about supervised
learning. And the idea is that, in
supervised learning, in every example in
our data set, we are told what is the
"correct answer" that we would have
quite liked the algorithms have predicted
on that example. Such as the price of the
house, or whether a tumor is malignant or
benign. We also talked about the
regression problem. And by regression,
that means that our goal is to predict a
continuous valued output. And we talked
about the classification problem, where
the goal is to predict a discrete value
output. Just a quick wrap up question:
Suppose you're running a company and you
want to develop learning algorithms to
address each of two problems. In the first
problem, you have a large inventory of
identical items. So imagine that you have
thousands of copies of some identical
items to sell and you want to predict how
many of these items you sell within the
next three months. In the second problem,
problem two, you'd like--  you have lots of
users and you want to write software to
examine each individual of your
customer's accounts, so each one of your
customer's accounts; and for each account,
decide whether or not the account has been
hacked or compromised. So, for each of
these problems, should they be treated as
a classification problem, or as a
regression problem? When the video pauses,
please use your mouse to select whichever
of these four options on the left you
think is the correct answer. So hopefully,
you got that this is the answer. For
problem one, I would treat this as a
regression problem, because if I have, you
know, thousands of items, well, I would
probably just treat this as a real value,
as a continuous value. And
treat, therefore, the number of items I sell,
as a continuous value. And for the
second problem, I would treat that as a
classification problem, because I might
say, set the value I want to predict with
zero, to denote the account has not been
hacked. And set the value one to denote an
account that has been hacked into. So just
like, you know, breast cancer, is,
zero is benign, one is malignant. So I
might set this be zero or one depending on
whether it's been hacked, and have an
algorithm try to predict each one of these
two discrete values. And because there's a
small number of discrete values, I would
therefore treat it as a classification
problem. So, that's it for supervised
learning and in the next video I'll talk
about unsupervised learning, which is the
other major category of learning algorithms.