In this video, I'd like to
tell you how to write
control statements for your
Octave programs, so things
like "for", "while" and "if" statements
and also how to define and use functions.
Here's my Octave window. Let
me first show you how to use a "for" loop.
I'm going to start by setting v
to be a 10 by
1 vector 0.
Now, here's I write
a "for" loop for I equals 1 to 10.
That's for I equals Y colon 10.
And let's see, I'm
going to set V of I
equals two to the
power of I, and finally
end.
The white space does not matter,
so I am putting the spaces
just to make it look nicely indented,
but you know spacing doesn't matter.
But if I do this, then the
result is that V gets
set to, you know, two to
the power one, two to the power two, and so on.
So this is syntax for I
equals one colon 10 that
makes I loop through the
values one through 10.
And by the way, you can also do
this by setting your
indices equals one to
10, and so the
indices in the array from one to 10.
You can also write for I equals indices.
And this is actually the same as if I equals one to 10.
You can do, you know, display
I and this would do the same thing.
So, that is a "for" loop,
if you are familiar with "break"
and "continue", there's "break" and
"continue" statements, you can
also use those inside loops
in octave, but first
let me show you how a while loop works.
So, here's my vector
V. Let's write the while loop.
I equals 1, while I
is less than or equal to
5, let's set
V I equals one hundred
and increment I by
one, end.
So this says what?
I starts off equal to
one and then I'm going
to set V I equals one
hundred and increment I by
one until I is, you know, greater than five.
And as a result of that,
whereas previously V was this powers of two vector.
I've now taken the first
five elements of my vector
and overwritten them with this value one hundred.
So that's a syntax for a while loop.
Let's do another example.
Y equals one while
true and here
I wanted to show you how to use a break statement.
Let's say V I equals 999
and I equals i+1
if i equals 6 break and
end.
And this is also our first
use of an if statement, so
I hope the logic of this makes sense.
Since I equals one and, you know, increment loop.
While repeatedly set V I equals 1
and increment i by 1,
and then when 1 i
gets up to 6, do a
break which breaks here although
the while do and so, the
effective is should be to take
the first five elements of this
vector V and set them to 999.
And yes, indeed, we're taking
V and overwritten the first five elements with 999.
So, this is the
syntax for "if" statements, and
for "while" statement, and notice the end.
We have two ends here.
This ends here ends the if statement
and the second end here ends the while statement.
Now let me show you the more general syntax for
how to use an if-else statement.
So, let's see, V 1
is equal to 999, let's
type V1 equals to 2 for this example.
So, let me type
if V 1 equals 1 display the value as one.
Here's how you write an else
statement, or rather here's an
else if: V 1 equals
2. This is, if in case that's true in our example, display
the value as 2, else
display, the value is not one or two.
Okay, so that's a  if-else
if-else statement it ends.
And of course, here we've just
set v 1 equals 2, so hopefully, yup,
displays that the value is 2.
And finally, I don't
think I talked about this earlier, but
if you ever need to exit Octave,
you can type the exit command and
you hit enter that will cause Octave
to quit or the 'q'--quits
command also works.
Finally, let's talk about
functions and how to define
them and how to use them.
Here's my desktop, and I
have predefined a file
or pre-saved on my desktop a file called "squarethisnumber.m".
This is how you define functions in Octave.
You create a file called, you know,
with your function name and then ending in .m,
and when Octave finds
this file, it knows that this
where it should look for the definition of the function "squarethisnumber.m".
Let's open up this file.
Notice that I'm using the
Microsoft program Wordpad to open up this file.
I just want to encourage you, if
your using Microsoft Windows, to
use Wordpad rather than
Notepad to open up these
files, if you have a
different text editor that's fine
too, but notepad sometimes messes up the spacing.
If you only have Notepad, that should
work too, that could work
too, but if you
have Wordpad as well, I
would rather use that or some
other text editor, if you have a different text editor for editing your functions.
So, here's how you define the function in Octave.
Let me just zoom in a little bit.
And this file has just three lines in it.
The first line says function Y equals square root
number of X, this tells
Octave that I'm gonna return
the value Y, I'm gonna
return one value and that
the value is going to
be saved in the variable Y
and moreover, it tells Octave
that this function has one argument,
which is the argument X,
and the way the function
body is defined, if Y equals X squared.
So, let's try to call
this function "square", this number
5, and this actually
isn't going to work, and
Octave says square this number it's undefined.
That's because Octave doesn't know where to find this file.
So as usual, let's use PWD,
or not in my directory,
so let's see this c:\users\ang\desktop.
That's where my desktop is.
Oops, a little typo there.
Users ANG desktop
and if I now type square
root number 5, it returns the
answer 25.
As kind of an advanced feature, this
is only for those of you
that know what the term search path means.
But so if you
want to modify the Octave
search path and you
could, you just think of
this next part as advanced
or optional material.
Only for those who are either
familiar with the concepts of
search paths and permit languages,
but you can use the
term addpath, safety colon,
slash users/ANG/desktop to
add that directory to the
Octave search path so that
even if you know, go to
some other directory I can
still, Octave still knows
to look in the users ANG
desktop directory for functions
so that even though I'm in
a different directory now, it still
knows where to find the square this number function.
Okay?
But if you're not familiar
with the concept of search path, don't worry
about it.
Just make sure as you use
the CD command to go to
the directory of your function before
you run it and that actually works just fine.
One concept that Octave has
that many other programming
languages don't is that it
can also let you define
functions that return multiple values or multiple arguments.
So here's an example of that.
Define the function called square
and cube this number X
and what this says is this
function returns 2 values, y1 and y2.
When I set down, this
follows, y1 is squared, y2 is execute.
And what this does is this really returns 2 numbers.
So, some of you depending
on what programming language you use,
if you're familiar with, you know, CC++ your offer.
Often, we think of the function as return in just one value.
But just so the syntax in Octave
that should return multiple values.
Now back in the Octave window. If
I type, you know, a, b equals
square and cube this
number 5 then
a is now equal to
25 and b is equal to
the cube of 5 equal to 125.
So, this is often
convenient if you needed to define
a function that returns multiple values.
Finally, I'm going to show
you just one more sophisticated example of a function.
Let's say I have a data set
that looks like this, with data points at 1, 1, 2, 2, 3, 3.
And what I'd like
to do is to define an
octave function to compute the cost
function J of theta for different values of theta.
First let's put the data into octave.
So I set my design
matrix to be 1,1,1,2,1,3.
So, this is my design
matrix x with x0, the
first column being the said
term and the second term being
you know, my the x-values of my three training examples.
And let me set
y to be 1-2-3 as
follows, which were the y axis values.
So let's say theta
is equal to 0 semicolon 1.
Here at my desktop, I've
predefined does cost function
j and if I
bring up the definition of that function it looks as follows.
So function j equals cost function
j equals x y
theta, some commons, specifying
the inputs and then
vary few steps set m
to be the number trading examples
thus the number of rows in x.
Compute the predictions, predictions equals
x times theta and so
this is a common that's wrapped
around, so this is probably the preceding comment line.
Computer script errors by, you know, taking
the difference between your predictions and
the y values and taking the
element of y squaring and then
finally computing the cost
function J. And Octave knows
that J is a value I
want to return because J appeared here in the function definition.
Feel free by the way to pause
this video if you want
to look at this function
definition for longer and
kind of make sure that you understand the different steps.
But when I run it in
Octave, I run j equals
cost function j x y theta.
It computes. Oops, made a typo there.
It should have been capital X. It
computes J equals 0 because
if my data set was,
you know, 123, 123 then setting, theta 0
equals 0, theta 1 equals
1, this gives me exactly the
45-degree line that fits my data set perfectly.
Whereas in contrast if I set
theta equals say 0, 0,
then this hypothesis is
predicting zeroes on everything
the same, theta 0 equals 0,
theta 1 equals 0 and
I compute the cost function
then it's 2.333 and that's
actually equal to 1 squared,
which is my squared error on
the first example, plus 2 squared,
plus 3 squared and then
divided by 2m, which is
2 times number of training examples,
which is indeed 2.33 and
so, that sanity checks that
this function here is, you
know, computing the correct cost
function and these are the couple examples
we tried out on our
simple training example.
And so that sanity tracks
that the cost function J,
as defined here, that it
is indeed, you know, seeming to compute
the correct cost function, at least
on our simple training set
that we had here with X
and Y being this
simple training example that we solved.
So, now you know how
to right control statements like for loops,
while loops and if statements
in octave as well as how to define and use functions.
In the next video, I'm
going to just very quickly
step you through the logistics
of working on and
submitting problem sets for
this class and how to use our submission system.
And finally, after that, in
the final octave tutorial video,
I wanna tell you about vectorization, which
is an idea for how to
make your octave programs run much fast.