In the last video, we talked
about the recommender system problem,
where for example, you may
have a set of movies and you
may have a set of users,
each of whom has rated
some subset of the movies,
rated the movies 1 to
5 stars or 0 to 5
stars, and what I would like
to do, is look at
these users and predict how
they would have rated other movies that they have not yet rated.
In this video, I would like
to talk about our first approach
to building a recommender system, this
approach is called content based recommendations.
Here's our data set from before,
and just to remind you of a
bit of notation, I was using
Nu to denote the number
of users, and so that's equal
to 4, and Nm
to denote the number of movies, I have five movies.
So, how do I predict
what these missing values would be?
Let's suppose that for each
of these movies, I have a
set of features for them.
In particular, lets say that
for each of the movies I have two features,
which I'm going to denote X1 and
X2, where X1 measures the degree
to which a movie is a
romantic movie and X2 measures
the degree to which a movie is an action movie.
So if you take a movie
Love at last, you know,
0.9 rating on the
romance scale, it is a
highly romantic movie but zero on
the action scale, so almost no
action in that
movie. Romance forever was 1.0,
lot of romance and 0.01 action,
I don't know maybe
there's a minor car crash in
that movie or something, so little bit of action.
Skipping one let's do
Swords vs,. karate, maybe that
has a zero romance rating
and no romance at all in that
but plenty of action and you know, non-stop car chases.
Maybe again there is
tiny bit of romance in
that movie, but mainly action,
and and Cute puppies of
love again but mainly a romance
movie with no action at all.
So if we have features
like these then each movie
can be represented with a feature vector.
Let's take movie 1, so just
call these movies you know, movies 1 2, 3, 4 and 5.
For my first movie,
Love at last, I have
my two features, 0.9 and
0, and so these are features
X1 and X2, and
let's add an extra feature
as usual, which is my
interceptor feature X0, which is equal to 1
and so, putting these together,
I would then have a feature X1,
the superscript 1 denotes it's
the feature vector for my first
movie, and this feature
vector is equal to one.
The first one there is this interceptor,
and then my two features 0.9, 0,
like so.
So, for Love at last, I
would have a feature vector X1,
for the movie Romance Forever, we
have the separate feature vector
X2 and so on, and
for Swords vs. karate I would
have a different feature vector x superscript 5.
Also, consistent with our
early notation that we were
using, we're going to set N
to be the number of features, not
counting this X zero
intercept term so n is
equal to two because we have
two features x1 and x2
capturing the degree of romance
and the degree of action in each
movie.
Now in order
to make predictions, here is one thing we could do,
which is that we could treat predicting
the ratings of each user
as a separate linear regression problem. So
specifically lets say that for each
user j we are going
to learn a parameter vector theta
J which would be in R3 in this case,
more generally theta j would
be in r n+1, where
n is the number of features,
not counting the intercept term, and we're going
to predict user J as
rating movie I, with just
the inner product between the parameters
vector theta and the features "XI".
So, let's take a specific example.
Let's take user one.
So that would be Alice and
associated with Alice would
be some parameter vector,
theta 1 and our
second user Bob will be
associated, with a different
parameter vector theta 2.
Carol will be associated with a
different parameter vector theta
3 and Dave a different
parameter vector, theta 4. So
lets say we want to make a
prediction for what Alice will
think of the movie, Cute
puppies of love. Well that
movie is going to have some
parameter vector X3, where
we have that X3 is going
to be equal to 1
which is my intercept term, and
then 0.99, and then 0.
And let's say for this
example, let's say that you
know we have somehow already gotten
a parameter vector theta 1
for Alice--we we will
say later exactly how
we come up with this parameter
vector--but let's
just say for now that you
know some unspecified learning algorithm
has learned the parameter vector
theta 1 and it is
equal to 0 5 0. And so
our prediction for this
entry is going to
be equal to theta 1,
that is Alice's parameter vector,
transpose X3, that
is the feature vector for
the Cute Puppies of Love movie number 3.
And so the inner
product between these two vectors
is going to be 5 x 0.99.
Which is equal to 4.95.
And so my prediction for value this
over here is going to be 4.95.
And maybe that seems like a
reasonable value, if indeed
this is my parameter vector theta 1.
So all we doing here is
we are applying a different copy of
essentially linear regression for each
user and we are saying
that what Alice does, is
Alice has seem some parameter vector
theta 1 that she uses,
that we use to predict
her ratings as a
function of how romantic and how
action packed the movie is
and Bob, and Carol, and
Dave each of them have a
different linear function of the
romantic-ness and action-ness or the degree
of romance and the degree of action
in a movie,
and that that is how we're going to predict their star ratings.
More formally here is
how we can write down the problem.
Our notation is that RIJ
is equal to one, if
user J has rated movie I,
and YIJ is the rating
of that movie if that rating exists.
That is if that user has actually
rated that movie. And
on the previous slide we also
defined theta J which
is a parameter for each user XI
which is a feature vector for specific
movie and for each user
and each movie you would predict
that rating, as follows.
So let me introduce,
just temporarily, introduce one extra
bit of notation mj, we
are gonna use mj to denote the
number of users rated by movie
j, we're gonna need this
notation only for this slide. Now, in order to learn
the parameter vector for
theta j, well, how can we do so?
This is basically a linear regression problem.
So what we can do, is
just choose a parameter vector, theta j,
so the predicted value
here are as close
as possible to the values
that we observed in our training set, the values we observed in our data.
So, let's write that down.
In order to learn the
parameter vector theta j, let's minimize over
my parameter vector theta j,
of sum--
and I want to sum
over all movies that user
j has rated--so we write this as sum
over all values of i
that is a colon rij equals 1.
So the way to read this summation index is
this is summation over all
the values of i, so that
r i j is equal to 1.
So this is going to be summing over all the
movies that user j has rated.
And then I am going to
compute theta j
transpose xi so
that's the prediction of user
j's rating on movie i,
minus y i j,
so that's the actual observed rating squared,
and then, let me just divide
by the number of movies
that user J, has
actually rated, so just divide by 1 over 2MJ.
And so this is
just like the least squares regression,
it's just like linear regression
where we want to choose
the parameter vector theta J, to minimize this type of squared error term.
And if you want to, you can
also add in a regularization term
so plus lambda over 2m, and
this is really 2MJ because,
this as if we have MJ examples right?
Because if user J has
rated that many movies, it's
sort of like we have that many data points with which to fit
the parameters theta J. And then
let me add in my usual
regularization term here of
theta J K squared.
As usual this sum is from
K equals 1 through N
so here theta J is
going to be an N plus
1 dimensional vector where,
in our early example, n was equal to two,
but more generally, n is
the number of features we have per movie.
And so as usual we don't regularize over theta 0.
We don't regularize over the
biased term because the sum is
from K1 through N. If
you minimize this as
a function of theta J you get a
good solution, you get a
pretty good estimate of a parameter vector theta j
with which to make the predictions
for user J's movie ratings.
For recommender systems, we're going
to change this notation a little
bit. So to simplify the subsequent math,
I'm actually going to get rid of this term MJ.
So that's just a constant right
so I can delete it without changing
the value of theta J that
I get out of this optimization,
so if you imagine taking this
whole equation, taking this
whole expression and multiplying it by
MJ and get rid of that constant, and when
I minimize this I should still get
the same value of theta J as before.
So, just to repeat what
we wrote on the previous slide, here
is our optimization objective: In order
to learn theta J, which is
a parameter for user J,
we're going to minimize over theta j
this optimization objectives. So
this is our usual squared
error term and then this is our regularization term.
Now of course in building
a recommender system we don't
just want to learn parameters
for a single user, we want
to learn parameters for all of
our users, I have n subscript u
users, so I want to
learn all of these parameters and
so what I'm going to do
is take this minimization, take
this optimization objective and just add an extra summation there.
So, you know, this expression here
with the one half on top again, so
it's exactly the same
as what we have on top except
that now, instead of just
doing this for a specific user theta
J, I'm going to sum
my objective over all of
my users and then minimize
this overall optimization objective.
Minimize this overall cost function.
And when I minimize this
as a function of theta 1,
theta 2, up to
theta NU, I will
get a separate parameter
vector each user and
I can then use that
to make predictions for all of
my users for all of
my N subscript u users.
So putting everything together, this
was our optimization objective on
top and to give
this thing a name, I'll just call this
J of theta 1,
dot, dot, dot theta NU.
So J as usual is my
optimization objective which I'm trying to minimize.
Next, in order to actually
do the minimization, if you
were to derive the gradient
descent updates, these are
the equations you would get,
so you would take theta
JK and subtract from
it alpha, which is the learning rate, times these terms here on the right.
So we have slightly different cases
so when K equals 0 and when K is not
equal to 0, because our regularization
term here regularizes only the
values of theta JK for
K not equal to zero. So
we don't regularize theta 0
so the slightly different updates
for k equals zero, and k not equal to 0.
And this term, over
here, for example is just a partial
derivative with respect to your parameter,
that of your
optimization objective, right?
And so, this is just
gradient descent and I've
already computed the derivatives and plugged them into here.
If these gradient
descent updates look a
lot like what we had for
linear regression, that's because these
are essentially the same as linear regression.
The only minor difference is that
for linear regression we have
these 1 over M terms
- it's really 1
over MJ - but
because earlier when we were
deriving the optimization objective
we got rid of this, that's why we don't have this 1 over M term.
But otherwise it's really sum over
my training examples of, you
know, the error times
XK plus that regularization
term contributes to the derivative.
So if you are using
gradient descent, here is how
you can minimize the cost
function j, to learn all
the parameters, and using these
formulas for the derivatives, if
you want, you can also plug them
into a more advanced optimization
algorithm like cluster gradient or
LBFGS or what have you, and use
that to try to minimize the cost function J as well.
So hopefully you now know
how you can apply essentially a
variation on linear regression in
order to predict different movie ratings by different users.
This particular algorithm is called
a content based recommendations, or
content based approach because we
assume that we have available
to us, features for the different movies.
So we have features that
capture what is the
content of these movies. How romantic is this movie?
How much action is in this movie?
And we are really using features of the
content of the movies to make our predictions.
But for many movies we
don't actually have such features,
or it may be very difficult to get
such features for all of
our movies, for all
of whatever items we are trying to sell.
So in the next video, we'll
start to talk about an approach
to recommender systems that isn't
content based and does not
assume that we have
someone else giving us all of these features,
for all of the movies in our data set.